A Guide to the Papers of Miloš Velimirović 1933-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Miloš Velimirović1933-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13082-b
This collection consists of ca. 1400 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, by Miloš Velimirović, 107 Cliff Custer Ct., Bridgewater, Virginia 22812, on August 17, 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
Retired University of Virginia professor of music, Miloš Velimirović was born December 10, 1922, in Belgrade. He studied at the Belgrade Academy of Music and the University of Belgrade, where he earned a diploma in the history of fine arts. He later earned an MA and PhD at Harvard and then served on the faculty at Yale, 1957-1969, then the University of Wisconsin until 1973 and finally the University of Virginia until his retirement in 1993. A prolific writer of articles in scholarly journals, he also edited numerous other publications and wrote many reviews of books and recordings. Some of his seminal work has focused on the relationship between Slavic and Greek chant melodies of the Slavonic heirmoi.
Albert J. Swan was a member of an English family who settled in Russia, where he was born on October 9, 1890, at St. Petersburg, where he also attended the St. Petersburg Conservatory. He left to study law, languages and music at Oxford, England, emigrating to the United States in the 1920s. He taught first at the University of Virginia, and then jointly at Haverford and Swarthmore Colleges from 1926 until his retirement in 1959. Swan was first recognized as a writer on music and as a musicologist interested in the relationship between Russian church chant and folk song. His work as a composer produced four piano sonatas, six quartets, and much liturgical choral music, written mostly to old Slavonic texts for the Orthodox church, including a complete setting of the extensive Orthodox service, among others. He died on October 2, 1970, in Haverford, Pennsylvania.
Pavel Chesnokov was born on November 5, 1877, in Voskresensk. His father was a music teacher and conductor, and his mother was a singer. He was enrolled in the Moscow Synodal Choir School as a child where he remained as a faculty member after his graduation. He composed music for the services of the Orthodox Church and in 1913 enrolled in the Moscow Conservatory. Until his death in Moscow on March 14, 1944, he was occupied primarily with the teaching of choral techniques and conducting.
Scope and Content
The Miloš Velimirović papers consist of ca. 1400 items (3 Hollinger boxes, 1.5 linear feet), 1933-1990, donated by musicologist and scholar Miloš Velimirović, a specialist on medieval chants of the Eastern Orthodox Churches and Eastern European music. The bulk of the papers consist of personal and professional correspondence. Personal correspondence includes letters to and from friends and acquaintances and holiday greeting cards and newsletters. Correspondence is mainly in English but other languages include Russian, German, and French. Professional correspondence includes itineraries for travel to and reports on academic conferences, letters of recommendations for employment, critiques and editing of scholarly and academic writings, draft manuscripts of journal articles, and copies of papers written by music specialists on a variety of topics. There are also a number of papers related to Russian-born composer Alfred Swan, a colleague and friend of Velimirović. These include biographical and autobiographical materials, correspondence, and materials related to a collection of Swan papers donated in the 1990s to the University of Virginia where Swan taught in the 1920s. Of interest are accounts of Swan's experiences in revolutionary Russia and his ultimately successful effort to leave that war-torn country. Included in the Swan materials are papers related to Russian composer Pavel Chesnokov. Velimirović assembled the papers while preparing for publication in the United States all of Chesnokov's available letters. They include copies of correspondence written in the 1930s by Chesnokov to Swan and one of his students, John Davison. There are also several articles written by Swan on Russian church music, folk songs, and liturgical chant.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three series. Series I: Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically by topic and reverse chronologically by correspondent. Series II: International Musicological Society 1977 Congress Presentation. Series III: Alfred J. Swan papers.
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, A-Bu 1963-1984 (Box-folder 1:1)
    Michael Adamis 1963-1972; Micheal Amargianikas 1972-1978; Lois Anderson 1973; Theodor Antoniou 1983; John Baron 1971-1975 (includes typewritten paper "Secular Spanish solo song in non-Spanish sources 1599- 1640"); Bojan Bujic 1967-1984
  - Correspondence, By-Kr 1963-1984 (Box-folder 1:2)
    David Bynum 1984; Olga Dobsky-Gubbenet 1970; Ivan Dujcev 1969; Harry Elzinga 1974-1977 Emil Georgiev 1979-1982; Wolf Geseman 1981; Carol Green 1969-1973; Manolis Hadjiyakoumis 1972, 1976 Father Hieromonk Ioannikios 1973-1975; Alvin Johnson 1963-1964; Aleksander Petrovich Kazhdan 1980; Barisa Krekic 1965-1976
  - Correspondence, Dmitri (Jim) Conomos 1977-1984 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence, Dmitri (Jim) Conomos 1970-1976 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence, Markos Dragoumis 1966-1990 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence, Markos Dragoumis 1963-1965 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence, Dumbarton Oaks Colleagues 1973-1978 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence, Dumbarton Oaks Colleagues 1961-1972 (Box-folder 2:1)
  - Correspondence, K-Li 1966-1977 (Box-folder 2:2)
    Venelin Krstev 1966-1975; Albina Nikandrovna Kruchinina 1974; Stefan Lazarov 1966-1977; Robert Gerald (Gerry) Livingston 1976
  - Correspondence, Lo-Mid 1966-1984 (Box-folder 2:3)
    Lewis Lockwood 1975-1981; William C. Loerke 1971-1978; Horace G. Lunt 1966-1979 (includes pamphlet "On the Language of Old Rus: Some Questions and Suggestions"); Hugh MacDonald 1975; Father Laurence Mancuso 1975; Cyril Mango 1974; Margarita Mazo 1984; Erik and Corelyn Midelfort 1976-1980
  - Correspondence, Mih-Par 1972-1985 (Box-folder 2:4)
    Vasa D. Mihailovich 1975-1979; K. Mitsakis 1972-1974; Bain and Skipper Murray 1970-1978; Greg and Evelyn Myers 1983-1985; Kenneth Naylor 1980-1981; Dimitri Obolensky 1981; Sir Cecil Parrott 1976-1977 (includes typewritten transcript to BBC radio broadcast "The Twilight of a Dynasty" about King Peter of Yugoslavia
  - Correspondence, Pat-Sc 1964-1981 (Box-folder 2:5)
    Christos Patrinelis 1970-1973; Andrzej Poppe 1974; Jorgen Raasted 1978; Neil Ratliff 1977; Katy Romanou 1973-1975; Alex Schenker 1981; Brooks Shepard 1964; Orville Shetney 1974-1976; Thomas Schleis 1973-1974
  - Correspondence, Stephen R. Reynolds (includes typed paper 'Observations on the Ukrainian Tradition in Religious Music') 1973-1982 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Correspondence, Se-W 1965-1985 (Box-folder 3:1)
    Rhoda Semel 1979; Kent Smith 1973; Ivo Supicic 1967-1977 (includes reprint "Science on Music and Values in Music"); James and Gilan Tocco 1976; William R. Tyler 1974; Constantin Trypanis 1965-1970; Alexander Tumanov 1976; Kathy Utter 1980; Vladimir Vavrinek 1972-1974; Arthur Voobus 1980; Speros Vryonis 1969-1970; Wayne S. Vucinich 1984-1985; Tom and Charlotte Walker 1976
  - Grigorios Th. Stathis (includes two papers: "Some Problems of the Old & New Methods of Byzantine Musical Notation Discussed in an Analysis of a Stichiron" and "Some Problems of the Old 'Synoptic' & New 'Analytical' Methods of Byzantine Musical Notation Discussed in an Analysis of a Stichiron" 1969-1972 (Box-folder 3:2)
  - Correspondence, A. Duane White 1970-1985 (Box-folder 3:3)
  - Correspondence, Wi 1970-1985 (Box-folder 3:4)
- Series II: International Musicological Society 1977 Congress Presentation by Velimirović "Use and Abuse of Folk Music" 1977 (Box-folder 3:5)
- Series III: Alfred J. Swan Papers 1933-1976
  - Swan, 2nd Version of Reminiscences 1962 (Box-folder 3:6)
  - Swan, Biography and Autobiography n.d. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - Swan, Correspondence with P.G. Chesnokov 1933-1975 (Box-folder 3:8)
  - Swan, Miscellaneous Papers and Photographs 1933-1934, 1963-1976 (Box-folder 3:9)
  - Swan, Published Materials 1940-1967 (Box-folder 3:10)
    The Znamenny Chant of the Russian Church and the Nature of the Russian Folk-Song; Towards a Restoration of the Znamenny Chant; On the Quest of the Sources of Music; Die russische Musik im 17. Jahrhundert; Maksym Vyktorovich...; The Present State of Research on Church Music in the USSR; Notes on the Old Liturgical Chant of the Russian Church and the Russian Folk Song